Next
example:
Again a UML state diagram, which we
are to transform into a flat state diagram.
This time no hierarchical
state, but a region state.
Characteristics of this example would be that
there are regions, but still no history.
And there is
a final state.
We will only ever have that on the outside,
if at all (in this kind of state diagram,
which is what we
want to use for flat-knocking).
Now what would
be the approach here?
Well, first of all, outside the region
we just proceed as before, that is,
as it was in
Example 1 as a recipe.
So keep
simple states.
Translate entries and exits at
the edge of hierarchical states appropriately.
This will later
also affect region entries/exits.
Keep transitions between outer states
also simple and keep only the
outermost start
state as such.
Outside regions we will
do exactly the same.
For now, we'll ignore this part
here, and decide what to do outside.
Here we will keep A and G, and
that A is (and will remain) the start state.
What happens
to the regions?
We actually want, with such a
parallel representation of regions, that always
at the same time a state from
one region and a state from the
other region are active, when we are
in this part of the state diagram.
That is, with these three states and these
two states, we now have to form pairs.
This means the cross
product between the states.
Let there be a BE state, a CE,
a DE, a BF, a CF, a DF.
So just the cross product between the
sets of the substates of those two regions.
So that will explain
how we proceed in here.
Then, of course, there
have to be appropriate transitions.
For example, if we're in the BE
state and a b is triggered, that
will lead to
the new CE state.
Just this parallel processing, how in that case
the E just doesn't change, but B becomes C.
This must be reflected in the transition
between corresponding states of the cross product.
Or if we would have a b below here, then it
would have to be so that with the b from the
state BE to CF is transferred,
because of this parallelism, which is present.
We're sort of translating the behavior,
in these two parallel regions, into
transitions between the
cross product states.
That explains how we deal
with the part in here,
making parallelism explicit, at the
level of the cross product states.
Then we have to
deal with the edge again.
What happens when we enter
or leave a region state.
For this, we will
basically just translate again
what then these
entries and exits mean.
According to the introduced
meaning of these different
ways of entering
and leaving states.
What we had already
done so far, on artificial
examples, we can use just
here for the flat knocking.
Let's make it
concrete for this example.
Outside the region, we proceed
as before, so we keep things.
This now leads
to this constellation.
Because there is hardly anything outside the region state,
we can only keep the A and the G,
with the respective marking
as start and end state.
Then this would be
what happens outside the region.
Then, of course, what is more
exciting is what happens inside the region.
And there the first, most important step is this
cross product of the sets of states of the regions.
Because we have these two regions here, with
the 2- and 3-element set respectively, and we're
supposed to form the cross product
between them, we now get six states.
Namely all pairs: once B, C, D paired
with E, once B, C, D paired with F.
That results as state set
first of all from this part.
Here, of course, there must
be some transitions in between.
And these are simply the
ones that result from the regions.
If the b and c changes between B,
C, D, while the state from the other
region remains unchanged (because there are
no b or c transitions there), it
leads to the fact that we can
progress here independently of the second component.
On the other hand, in the other region
there is this e-transition, from E to F, where
B, C, D are not affected in the
other region because there is no e-transition there.
This then leads to the fact
that there are still these transitions.
Here always that must be
done, which results from the regions.
If necessary
also by parallel
executions, if actually times a
trigger occurs in both regions.
Then it can also
come to other arrows.
But in the concrete case here, this
picture results within the cross product set.
So we did that
outside the region as before.
In addition, the cross product
between the regions was formed.
Within the regions
corresponding transitions suitably translated.
Then it's still a matter of
the entries and exits at the edge.
Now, we have here these a, h, and
g transitions that enter or leave the region state.
We still have to give
translations for each of those.
The a transition
is very easy.
This was here a transition into
the region state by standard entry.
Then we know: we just choose
the starting state in each region.
So this transition from A through
a must lead to the pair BE.
That's exactly
what happens here.
So that
explains this translation.
What about
the g?
What did that look like
in the original UML state diagram?
That was leaving regions from
two very specific sub-states, namely
D in the first region
and F in the second.
That means, again, in translating to
this cross product, we then have
to have a transition with g from
the pair DF to the outer state G.
So that explains why
this transition starts right here
and not in any of the
other states from the cross product.
And then we're still
missing the translation of
how this h transition plays
out in the cross product.
That is a transition that explicitly leaves
only one state of the two regions, C.
This means that we are allowed to
leave this region state whenever C is present
in the first region (while it does not
matter what is present in the second region).
We are allowed to take this transition
whenever we are in state CE or CF.
This is what
happens right here.
The h is allowed to act
and lead to G to the outside
exactly when there is C in the first region (and
it does not matter what is in the second region).
This would also
solve this example.
So to this UML state
diagram belongs this flat state diagram.
The main idea
is just to form
the cross product and then
of course to enter suitable transitions.